it's July 31st 2023 this is Daniel and
this video is going to be using
perplexity.ai which is an AI based
conversational search engine
using perplexity.ai to learn and apply
active inference pretty fun conversation
that I just had a lot of epistemic and
pragmatic value
so
I started by using the new feature of
beta
from perplexity AI today which was the
ability to upload a file with several
other language models increasingly have
and I uploaded the 2022 active inference
textbooks
textbook and I first aim for defenses
write an elaborate PhD dissertation that
summarizes all domain aspects and
technical details of the active
inference textbook attached here's the
PDF and it didn't want to immediately go
for it but it gave some summary but I
was looking for something a lot deeper
than just an overall summary of the book
so I asked what is the free energy
principle and how is it related to
active inference
it's an interesting answer but I'm going
to keep on moving because there's some
really detailed things it gets to what
is expected free energy give multiple
explanations including the perspective
of math science and programming now here
I utilized The Limited number of copilot
runs five every four hours so this
engaged a sequential process of
searching the web
finding sources
different papers and YouTube channels
videos
and writing about broadly the aspects of
expected free energy epistemic value and
here extrinsic value but usually called
pragmatic value so it's a pretty good
representation
so I asked for more of an application
explain what epistemic value and
pragmatic value would represent in the
case of someone who wanted to turn on
their air conditioner to prevent
overheating however first had to find a
key that would unlock the air
conditioner's control panel again used
copilot search the web
looked at a bunch of sources
clarified and improved its understanding
of epistemic and pragmatic value
and relatively accurately describing the
epistemic value this represents the
agent's uncertainty about the
environment and the need to gather
information to reduce that uncertainty
in this scenario the epistemic values
associated with the agent's uncertainty
about the location of the key
by searching for the key the agent
reduces their uncertainty and gains
knowledge about the environment which is
considered valuable from an epistemic
perspective pragmatic value this
represents the agent's preferences or
goals which in this case is to turn on
the air conditioner to prevent
overheating
in the context of active inference the
agent's goal is to minimize the expected
free energy by finding the optimal
balance between epistemic and pragmatic
values in this scenario the agent needs
to gather information about the key's
location epistemic value
and take actions to turn on the air
conditioner pragmatic value to achieve
their goal and prevent overheating
again with copilot I asked right
comprehensive professional python style
pseudocode to fully simulate the
situation with the person air
conditioner and key
it asked for more information on what
size I wanted the world to be I said 20
by 20. it looked up some related
terms
discovered some agent-based modeling
repos
wrote a python style script I didn't run
it I just kept going
great
can you update the script to explicitly
utilize open source active inference
implementations for example using Pi mdp
Pi mdp could be used to specify the
generative model for the human agent
develop that as much as you can and then
I will be ready to provide more
technical information after
it asks what is what should the
generative model
container do
I said the person should have three
hidden physiological states too cold
just right too hot the ability to
observe temperature values on a 100
scale and the ability to move in the
grid within a three by three adjacency
Matrix there was some searching there
was the discovery of multiple papers
kaggle archive NIH research Gates
two of the model stream Pi mdp videos
from reactive inference Institute
and it specified the problem
giving what is a broadly
compatible but not complete or coherence
Pi mdp implementation
for for a number of reasons but again
it's a pseudo code and it gives a
disclaimer it's a high level
representation of the implementation and
you may need to adapt your specific
requirements and the pi mdp's Library
Syntax for more information on using pi
mdp you can refer to the official
documentation and the step-by-step
tutorial on active inference so those
pieces of information as PDFs or as
websites probably eventually or
currently could be already brought in to
the model
I said keep working with that remember
that action selection that the person
takes needs to consider the variational
free energy of sensory States the
temperature and their hidden internal
States physiological temperature
copilot did a search
implemented the variational free energy
now
what was very interesting was in the
code
it actually computed the expected free
energy
and I don't think it did variational at
all
in this updated pseudocode
we added the computation of the expected
free energy using the agent compute
expected free energy method the action
selection is now based on the efe
which considers both sensory States
temperature and hidden internal States
physiological temperature the agent
moves in the grid within a three by
three adjacency Matrix and unlocks the
air conditioner when it reaches the air
conditioner and has the key
I said we're not quite unexpected free
energy yet can you rewrite the script
with proper calculation of variational
free energy
approximating the model with the lowest
price which is the highest model
evidence
apologies for the confusion
there was some
infusion apparently
I can provide you with a modified
pseudocode that incorporates the concept
of variational free energy based on the
principles of active inference great
more code
more provocative code
a variational free energy
threshold-based calculations
well compute vfv is introduced this is
just pseudocode
you can Implement your specific vfv
calculation within this function
okay that sounds good
please note you'll need to replace the
placeholder code and compute the IP
function with your actual vfp
calculation based on your specific model
and requirements
so again keeping in mind that the
textbook is in the window
or something
write all the specifications and
considerations that would be important
in order to write the compute vfv
function based upon textbook equation
2.5 and anywhere else in the book that
is relevant
but variational free energy
again probably not
100 percent accurate
for example ICD is set here to be the
observation
Matrix
but that should be the prior
but in general it's it's
more accurate than not
so I went a little broader with give 11
different perspectives or
interpretations about what variational
free energy is think broadly we're
Global and intergenerational textbook
group
11 different perspectives
could argue whether they're all within a
kind of technical or scientific domain
but but
let's see if it can go broader
that's awesome can you comprehensively
describe expected free energy equation
2.6 in the textbook
expected free energy time Horizon action
selection
uncertainty
adaptation
computational complexity
model selection
overall expected free energy extends the
concept of variational free energy to
incorporate the expected future surprise
or prediction error it provides a useful
measure for guiding the agent's action
selection and adaptation in Dynamic and
uncertain environments 100 true
give 15 Salient concise provocative
points that convey expected free energy
to someone interested in embodied
embedded inactive approaches
15 points
if you were to derive a word list of the
17 most important terms to know from the
textbook what would it be I'm thinking
about words that are rare outside of
this textbook and overrepresented in
their syntactic abundance and semantic
Central centrality in this textbook
here are the 17 Salient and rare terms
from a textbook that are overrepresented
in their syntactic abundance and
semantic centrality here they are
active inference variational free energy
expected free energy generative model
Bayesian inference prediction error
surprise self-evidencing normative
framework message passing neurobiology
computational models procedural
knowledge belief updating sentient
behavior and activism unified theory
these terms are Central to the concepts
and theories presented in the textbook
and are important for understanding the
principles and implications of active
inference they provide a unique
perspective on how we perceive plan and
act in the world and how we can use
computational models to simulate and
model sentient Behavior
can you make a table where the rows are
those 17 items terms and there's a
second column for a synthetic definition
based on your best perspective
give us a table
active inference a normative framework
that characterizes Bayes optimal
behavior and cognition in living
organisms by minimizing the surprise of
their sensory observations
foreign
this is really interesting after this
conversation with your help I will be
doing some applied active inference
modeling something involving what is
discussed in chapter 3 chapter 4 chapter
6 and chapter 9. can you lay out a
technical agenda for me to completely
specify an active inference agent over
the next one month
I'm ready to work two hours per day with
focus and attention on this task and now
you are there to catalyze
so there's 15 points
to consider before doing that kind of
work
but I didn't like the list
so I said can you lay it out like a
table with a few clear Milestones that
would demonstrate clear progress like
for a PhD
and I said sure here's the table with a
few clear Milestones that would
demonstrate clear progress in specifying
an active inference agent over the next
month
Milestone one understanding active
inference
Milestone 2 study chapter 3 Implement
generative models explore chapter four
design active inference models chapter
6.
active inference industry time active
inference and continuous time
interestingly it mentions chapter 7
discrete time even though I didn't
mention chapter 7.
and it linked up six seven and eight and
nine
and fought it linked up
it linked up
from four
to nine
with the Milestone chapter alignment
but not
aligned for these three to mix it up
Milestone 10 Implement and refine models
Milestone 11 experiment and evaluate
and asked what would someone in your
position ask me in partying before I
head off to tackle these 11 milestones
and more
11 questions to keep in mind
so that's all for now thought it was a
pretty interesting and informative
conversation
I applaud
technically
what perplexity.ai is doing and I
look forward to seeing what uh people in
the textbook group
people who are looking at how to
understand the equations and the
contexts for different things in the
textbook
it would be awesome to
see how these
tools can help us learn and apply all
right till next time